Finding Aid for George W. Harms papers, 1915-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George W. Harms papers 1915-1988 1966-1988
Harms, George W., 1921-1993.
1 linear ft. and 1 outsize volume.
88556 Aa 2
Veteran of World War II, later commander of Erwin Prieskorn Post No. 46 of the American Legion, Ann Arbor, Michigan. Subject files relating to veterans activities and his involvement in issues of concern to veterans; minutes of meetings of Ann Arbor, Michigan, post of the American Legion; and scrapbook of American Legion Post No. 46 containing letters from servicemen in Vietnam and photographs of post activities; also other photographs and videotapes.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by George W. Harms (Donor No. 7587 ) in August 1988 and by Mrs. Harms in August 1993.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
George W. Harms was born in Detroit, Michigan on May 6, 1921. In 1943 he received his AB from the University of Michigan. While in college, Harms was a catcher for the University of Michigan varsity baseball team, 1940-1942, serving as captain in 1942. He was also a member of the Sigma Phi Epsilon fraternity, 1940-1943, serving as president in 1942.
Following college, Harms began active service with the United States Marine Corps. He served from 1943 until his honorable discharge with the rank of Sergeant in 1946. He was awarded two Purple Hearts and a Bronze Star for valor. In 1955, Harms was classified as a Disabled Combat Veteran.
A member of numerous community service and veteran organizations, Harms founded the Washtenaw County Detachment of the Marine Corps League in 1975 and co-founded the Military Order of the Purple Heart in 1982. He has been particularly active with the American Legion Post No. 46 (Ann Arbor) since 1965, serving as post commander in 1966.
Harms died June 30, 1993.
The George W. Harms collection has been arranged into four series: Biographical; Topical Files; American Legion Post No. 46; and Visual Materials. Most of the collection relates to his activities with the Ann Arbor American Legion post and with veterans affairs in general. Post No. 46 materials includes minutes, correspondence, a scrapbook, and some newspaper clippings dating from 1968 to 1988. The issues of concern to veterans and to Harms included government policies and procedures concerning soldiers listed as missing in action and relationships with their families, Veterans Administration policies toward disabled soldiers, veterans' benefits for survivors of soldiers killed in action, and anti-war protests in Ann Arbor in the 1960s.
Subjects:
American Legion. Erwin Prieskorn Post No. 46 (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.); Harms, George W., 1921-1993.; Veterans--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies, etc.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
American Legion. Erwin Prieskorn Post No. 46 (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Baseball.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Detroit.; Compulsory military service.; Detroit (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Lund, Don.; University of Michigan--Baseball.; Veterans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Videotapes.
- Biographical
  - Clippings and background information, 2 folders
- Topical Files (Box 1)
  - Americanism, October 1968-September 1971 (Box 1)
  - Boys and Girls County Government Day, November 1966-September 1976 (Box 1)
  - PFC Robert B. Huff case, March-November 1978 (Box 1)
  - Flag at Michigan-Navy Football game, September 1981 (Box 1)
  - Marine Corps League, November 1977-January 1978 (Box 1)
  - Memorial Home Association By-laws and minutes, July 1978-May 1980 (Box 1)
  - Michigan American Legion Baseball Committee meeting minutes, September 1967-April 1968 and undated (Box 1)
  - Military Order of the Purple Heart, April 1982-February 1988 (Box 1)
  - ROTC at University of Michigan, November 1969 (Box 1)
  - White Panthers vs. Community Response, July-August 1969 (Box 1)
- American Legion Post No. 46
  - Post Adjutant's Administrative Manual, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Minutes
    - 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Membership list, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1966-1967 (Volume 1)
    (includes letters from servicemen in Vietnam and photographs)
- Visual Materials
  - Photographs
    - American Legion, 1966-1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Harms Family, 1917-195? (Box 1)
    - UM Sports, 1921-197? (Box 1)
  - Videotape
    - Don Lund's Retirement Roast, February 9, 1992, VHS format; 2 hours, 3 min. (Box 1)